<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- $Id: xapi-req.xml,v 1.1.1.1 2002/01/30 09:46:42 lars Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE specification SYSTEM "sbk:/style/dtd/specification-v10.dtd">

<specification>

   <header>
      <title>XML Database API Draft Requirements</title>
      <version>2000-11-17</version>
      <type>Working Draft</type>
      <authors>
         <person name="Lars Martin" email="lars@smb-tec.com"/>
      </authors>
      <notice>
      This is an XML:DB Working Draft for review by all interested parties.
      It is a draft document and may be updated, replaced, or obsoleted by other
      documents at any time. It is inappropriate to use Working Drafts as reference 
      material or to cite them as other than &quot;work in progress&quot;. This work
      is part of the <link href="http://www.xmldb.org/">XML:DB Project</link>.
      </notice>
      <abstract>
      This document specifies goals and requirements for the XML:DB XML Database API.
      </abstract>
   </header>

   <body>

      <s1 title="XML Database API Requirements">

         <s2 title="Goals">
         
            <p>
            The goal of the XML:DB Initiative is to develop an Application Programming
            Interface (API) for XML Databases. To provide a wide usability the API must
            be specified as vendor-neutral. Furthermore it is the goal to use the API
            with any programming language. Using existing W3C publications the API
            specification includes as much as possible established recommendations.
            </p>

         </s2>
   
         <s2 title="Requirements">
   
            <p>
            The following key words are used throughout the document to specify the extent
            to which an item is a requirement for the work of the XML Database API Working Group:
            </p>
   
            <dl>
   
               <dt>MUST</dt>
               <dd>
               This word means that the item is an absolute requirement.
               </dd>
   
               <dt>SHOULD</dt>
               <dd>
               This word means that there may exist valid reasons not to treat this item as
               a requirement, but the full implications should be understood and the case
               carefully weighed before discarding this item.
               </dd>
            
               <dt>MAY</dt>
               <dd>
               This word means that an item deserves attention, but further study is needed
               to determine whether the item should be treated as a requirement.
               </dd>
   
            </dl>        
   
            <s3 title="General Requirements">
                  
               <dl>
                  <dt>Language Independence</dt>
                  <dd>The API <strong>MUST NOT</strong> preclude the usage with more than one
                  language binding.
                  </dd>

                  <dt>Textual Interface</dt>
                  <dd>The API MUST provide a textual representation of XML result sets.
                  </dd>

                  <dt>XML-API Interface</dt>
                  <dd>The API SHOULD provide a SAX or DOM based representation of XML
                  result sets.
                  </dd>
               </dl>
              
            </s3>
   
            <s3 title="API Functionality">

               <dl>
                  <dt>Insertion</dt>
                  <dd>The API MUST be able to store new Documents into the database.
                  An optional unique identifier MAY be assigned to this document.
                  </dd>

                  <dt>Retrieval</dt>
                  <dd>The API MUST provide the ability to retrieve Documents
                  from the database. The Document MUST be identified by a unique ID.
                  </dd>

                  <dt>Deletion</dt>
                  <dd>The API MUST be able to delete Documents from the Database.
                  The Document MUST be identified by a unique ID.
                  </dd>

                  <dt>Update</dt>
                  <dd>The API MUST provide the ability to update Documents.
                  The Document MUST be identified by a unique ID.
                  </dd>

                  <dt>Query Processing</dt>
                  <dd>The API MUST provide the ability to process queries. The
                   query facility MUST NOT assume the existence of a particular
                   Query Language.
                  </dd>

                  <dt>Collections</dt>
                  <dd>The API MUST provide the ability to support nested collections of
                  Documents.
                  </dd>

                  <dt>Transactions</dt>
                  <dd>The API MAY provide a transactional environment.
                  </dd>

               </dl>
   
            </s3>
            
         </s2>

      </s1>
   </body>

   <appendices>


      <s1 title="Changes made to Previous Versions">

         <s2 title="March 2, 2000">

            <ul>
               <li>Cleaned up wording and corrected typos</li>
            </ul>

         </s2>
         
         <s2 title="November 17, 2000">

            <ul>
               <li>IDs are no longer required attributes to identify documents for insertion</li>
               <li>completed some missing requirements</li>
            </ul>

         </s2>

      </s1>

      <s1 title="Normative References">

         <bl>
            <bi name="XML"
                href="http://www.w3.org/TR/1998/REC-xml-19980210"
                title="Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0" 
                authors="Tim Bray, Jean Paoli, C. M. Sperberg-McQueen"
                date="10 February 1998"/>
            <bi name="SAX" 
                href="http://www.megginson.com/SAX/index.html" 
                title="Simple API for XML (SAX) 2.0"
                authors="David Megginson"
                date="May 5, 2000"/>
            <bi name="DOM"
                href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2000/REC-DOM-Level-2-Core-20001113/" 
                title="Document Object Model (DOM) Level 2 Core Specification"
                authors="Arnaud Le Hors, Philippe Le Hegaret, Lauren Wood"
                date="November 13, 2000"/>
         </bl>

      </s1>

      <s1 title="Other References">

         <bl>
            <bi name="XUpdate"
                href="http://www.xmldb.org/xupdate/index.html"
                title="XUpdate XML Update Language"
                authors="XML:DB XUpdate Working Group"
                date="2000"/>
            <bi name="XML Query"
                href="http://www.w3c.org/TR/xmlquery-req"
                title="XML Query Requirements"
                authors="W3C XML Query Working Group"
                date="2000"/>
         </bl>

      </s1>

   </appendices>

</specification>


